Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers 1671-1936
MSS54304
Armes, Ethel, 1876-1945
500 items 3 containers 1.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, architectural plans, genealogical papers, maps, legal papers, clippings, and other material assembled by Armes in preparing her book, Stratford Hall: The Great House of the Lees (1936).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Armes, Ethel, 1876-1945.; Carter, Lucy Grymes Lee, 1786-1860. Lucy Grymes Lee Carter papers.; Corbin, Hannah Lee, 1728-1782. Hannah Lee Corbin papers.; Green, Duff, 1791-1875--Correspondence.; Greene Nathanael, 1742-1786--Correspondence.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804--Correspondence.; Hopkins, Cornelia Lee, 1780-1815. Cornelia Lee Hopkins papers.; Izard, Elizabeth Byrd Carter Shippen. Elizabeth Byrd Carter Shippen Izard papers.; Lee family.; Lee, Ann Hill Carter, 1773-1829. Ann Hill Carter Lee papers.; Lee, Anne Robinson McCarty, 1798-1840. Anne Robinson McCarty Lee papers.; Lee, Charles Carter, 1798-1871. Charles Carter Lee papers.; Lee, Elizabeth Collins, d. 1858. Elizabeth Collins Lee papers.; Lee, Henry, 1756-1818. Henry Lee papers.; Lee, Henry, 1787-1837. Henry Lee papers.; Lee, Mary Randolph Custis, 1807-1873. Mary Randolph Custis Lee papers.; Lee, Richard Bland, 1761-1827. Richard Bland Lee papers.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1794-1865. Richard Henry Lee papers.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870. Robert E. Lee papers.; Lee, Thomas, 1690-1750. Thomas Lee papers.; Livingston, Anne Home Shippen, 1763-1841. Anne Home Shippen Livingston papers.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Shippen, Alice Lee, 1736-1817. Alice Lee Shippen papers.; Shippen, Thomas Lee, 1765-1798. Thomas Lee Shippen papers.; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808. William Shippen papers.; Tyler, John, 1790-1862--Correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Correspondence.
Subjects
Agriculture--Virginia.; Plantations--Virginia.; Slavery--Virginia.
Places
Shirley Plantation (Va.); Stratford Hall (Va.); United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Virginia--Social life and customs.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers was given to the Library of Congress by Armes between 1936 and 1939.
Access and Restrictions
The Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers consists principally of photocopies and transcripts of documents found in other repositories. Armes collected and assembled these in preparation for her book, Stratford Hall: The Great House of the Lees (1936). Materials date from 1671 to 1936 and include family correspondence of the Lee and Shippen families pertaining mainly to life during the Revolutionary War period. The bulk of the correspondence is that of Henry "Lighthorse Harry" Lee, Revolutionary War general and father of Robert E. Lee, and Major Henry Lee, brother of Robert E. Lee. Subjects detailed in the correspondence include military activities during the Revolutionary War, politics and political appointments, financial affairs in the colonies, agriculture, planting, and slavery in Virginia, and family life on Shirley Plantation. Among other family members represented in the collection are Charles Carter Lee, Richard Bland Lee, Mary Randolph Custis and Robert E. Lee, Alice Lee Shippen, Thomas Lee Shippen, and William Shippen. One noteworthy item in the collection is a copy of a letter of former slave Eleanor Berry to Elizabeth Collins Lee, her previous mistress. Duff Green, Nathanael Greene, Alexander Hamilton, James Madison, John Tyler, and George Washington are among the more prominent correspondents in the collection.
Copies of architectural plans and drawings of various Lee family estates, family genealogies, legal papers, maps, and newspaper clippings are included in the collection. The few original documents in the Ethel Armes Collection of Lee Family Papers consist mainly of research notes and correspondence of Armes and pertain to her book. Of particular interest is a letter of Franklin D. Roosevelt to Armes; Roosevelt wrote the foreword to her book.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or name of person.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm82054304
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Armes, Ethel (b. 1876), 1932-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Carter, Lucy Grymes Lee (1786-1860), 1798-1813 (Box 1)
  - Corbin, Hannah Lee (1728-1782), 1759-1760 (Box 1)
  - Izard, Elizabeth Byrd Carter Shippen, 1799-1824, undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Ann Hill Carter (1773-1829), 1805-1816 (Box 1)
  - Lee, Anne Robinson McCarty, 1828-1837, undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Charles Carter (1798-1871), 1817-1868 (Box 1)
  - Lee, Cornelia (Cornelia Lee Hopkins) (1780-1815), 1801-1808, undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Elizabeth Collins (1747-1858), 1792, undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Elizabeth Collins, 1925-1927, undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Henry (1756-1818) (Box 1)
    - 1779-1816 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Lee, Henry (1787-1837) (Box 2)
    - 1816-1830 (Box 2)
    - 1831-1836 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Mary Randolph Custis (1806-1873), 1834-1871, undated (Box 2)
  - Lee, Richard Bland (1761-1827), 1811-1812 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Richard Henry (1794-1865), 1840 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Robert E. (1807-1870), 1840-1865 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Thomas (1690-1750), 1720-1750, undated (Box 1)
  - Shippen, Alice Lee (1736-1817), 1778, undated (Box 2)
  - Shippen, Nancy Lee (Anne Home Shippen Livingston) (1763-1841), undated (Box 2)
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee, 1783-1809 (Box 2)
  - Shippen, William, 1814 (Box 2)
- Other family correspondence, 1807-1825 (Box 2)
- General correspondence, 1753-1827, undated (Box 2)
- Armes, Ethel, research notes, circa 1930s (Box 2)
- Original documents, 1809-1895 (Box 2)
- Maps, 1671, 1775 (Box 2)
- Architectural plans and drawings of Lee family estates (Box 3)
- Copies of title pages from books in Lee family library (Box 3)
- Lee family genealogies (Box 3)
- Lee, Charles Carter, writings (Box 3)
- Legal papers (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings, 1870, undated (Box 3)
- Transcripts of letters, 1750-1891, undated (Box 3)